Guide to the Bernard Frank Dukore Collection of Peter Barnes
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Bernard Frank Dukore Collection of Peter Barnes
1958-2007
GEN MSS 625
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.35
(9 boxes)
The collection consists of material relating to Peter Barnes, which was created and accumulated by Bernard Frank Dukore in the course of his research on the work of the British dramatist and screenwriter. Material includes incoming and copies of outgoing correspondence between Dukore and Barnes, dating from 1978 to 2004; copies and typescripts of original plays, adaptations, and scripts by Peter Barnes, some of which are inscribed or annotated; audio recordings of BBC productions of Barnes's plays and copies of commercially-released films and television programs featuring scripts by Barnes on VHS and DVD-R; photographs and programs relating to the production of Barnes's plays; correspondence between Dukore and Gisele Joly, the French translator of Barnes's play Red Noses; transcripts of interviews with Barnes conducted by Dukore; and numerous clippings and photocopies of published writings by Barnes and about Barnes by Dukore.
Dukore, Bernard F., 1931-
Barnes, Peter, 1931-2004
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Bernard Frank Dukore on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2008, and gift of Bernard Frank Dukore, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 7 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 9 (electronic documents): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Peter Barnes (1931-2004)
Peter Barnes was a British dramatist, screenwriter, and film critic. His plays include The Ruling Class: A Baroque Comedy (1969), which was made into a film starring Peter O'Toole in 1972, Leonardo's Last Supper (1970), The Bewitched (1974), Red Noses (1985), Sunsets and Glories (1990), and Jubilee (2001). His screenplays include an adaptation of Elizabeth von Arnim's novel Enchanted April, for which he received an Academy Award nomination in 1992.
Bernard Frank Dukore (1931-)
Bernard Frank Dukore was a professor of drama and theater at the University of Hawaii from 1972 to 1986, and a University Distinguished professor of Theatre Arts and Humanities at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University from 1986 to 1997. He is the author of The Theatre of Peter Barnes (1981), American Dramatists, 1918-1945 (1984), and Barnestorm: The Plays of Peter Barnes (1995), as well as numerous other books, essays, and articles on theater.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material relating to Peter Barnes, which was created and accumulated by Bernard Frank Dukore in the course of his research on the work of the British dramatist and screenwriter. Material includes incoming and copies of outgoing correspondence between Dukore and Barnes, dating from 1978 to 2004; copies and typescripts of original plays, adaptations, and scripts by Peter Barnes, some of which are inscribed or annotated; audio recordings of BBC productions of Barnes's plays and copies of commercially-released films and television programs featuring scripts by Barnes on VHS and DVD-R; photographs and programs relating to the production of Barnes's plays; correspondence between Dukore and Gisele Joly, the French translator of Barnes's play Red Noses; transcripts of interviews with Barnes conducted by Dukore; and numerous clippings and photocopies of published writings by Barnes and about Barnes by Dukore.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1978-2004. II. Writings by Peters Barnes, 1960-2004. III. Audio-Visual Material, 1976-1992. IV. Other Papers, 1958-2007. This organization is largely based upon the order in which the material was received by the library.
Dramatists, English -- 20th Century; English drama -- 20th Century -- History and criticism; Motion picture authorship; Motion pictures -- England; Playwriting; Theater -- England; Audiocassettes; Photographs; Videocassettes; Born digital; Electronic documents; Barnes, Peter, 1931-2004; Dukore, Bernard F., 1931-
- Correspondence, 1978-2004; Series I; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence between Peter Barnes and Bernard F. Dukore, 1978-2004; 14 (Box 1)
- Writings by Peter Barnes, circa 1960-2000; Series II; 2.09 linear feet (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of copies and typescripts of final versions of original plays, adaptations, and scripts by Barnes, some of which are inscribed by Barnes or annotated by either Barnes or Dukore.
  - The Man with a Feather in His Hat, circa 1960 (Box 2)
  - The Time of the Barracudas, circa 1963 (Box 2)
  - Sclerosis, circa 1965 (Box 2)
  - Clap Hands, Here Comes Charlie (original), 1966 (Box 2)
  - Clap Hands, Here Comes Charlie (revised), 1991 (Box 2)
  - The Alchemist, circa 1970 (Box 2)
  - My Ben Jonson, circa 1972 (Box 2)
  - Eastward Ho!, circa 1973 (Box 2)
  - The Devil is an Ass, circa 1973 (Box 2)
  - The Bewitched, circa 1974 (Box 2)
  - The Two Hangmen: Brecht and Wedekind, circa 1976-1978 (Box 2)
  - Volpone, circa 1976 (Box 3)
  - A Eulogy of Baldness, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Bartholomew Fair, circa 1978 (Box 3)
  - Red Noses, Black Death, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Red Noses, circa 1985 (Box 3)
  - A Chaste Maid in Cheapside, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Antonio, circa 1977-1979 (Box 3)
  - The Silent Woman, circa 1979 (Box 3)
  - Don Juan and Faust, 1979 (Box 3)
  - The Shuttle, circa 1970-1990 (Box 3)
  - The Devil Himself, circa 1980 (Box 3)
  - The Atheist, circa 1980 (Box 3)
  - The Soldier's Fortune, circa 1981 (Box 4)
  - Somersaults, circa 1981 (Box 4)
  - The Dutch Courtesan, circa 1982 (Box 4)
  - A Barnes Half-Dozen, circa 1981 (Box 4)
    7 plays that would become "Barnes' People."
    - Confessions of a Primary Terrestrial Receiver and Communicator: Num III Mark I
    - The Jumping Mimuses of Byzantium
    - The End of the World--and After
    - Glory
    - Yesterday's News
    - The Theory and Practice of Belly Dancing
    - Rosa
  - A Mad World, My Masters, circa 1982 (Box 4)
  - Actors, circa 1983 (Box 4)
  - The Sprout, circa 1984 (Box 4)
    General note
    Produced as "The Primrose Path"
  - Barnes' People II, circa 1984 (Box 4)
    - Acting Exercise
    - Moondog Rogan and the Mighty Hamster
    - Worms
    - The Right Time and Place
    - It's Cold, Wanderer, It's Cold
    - Lament for Armenians and Grey Viruses
    - Silver Bridges
  - A Trick to Catch the Old One, circa 1985 (Box 4)
  - A Hand Witch of the Second Stage, circa 1985 (Box 4)
  - Woman of Paris, circa 1986 (Box 4)
    Typescript entitled "The Parisian," based on Henry Becque's "Woman of Paris" and "The Widow."
  - The Old Law, circa 1986 (Box 4)
  - Scenes from a Marriage, circa 1986 (Box 4)
  - The Magnetic Lady, circa 1987 (Box 4)
  - Nobody Here But Us Chickens, circa 1989 (Box 4)
  - Not as Bad As They Seem, 1982 (Box 5)
    Also broadcast under the rubric "Nobody Here But Us Chickens."
  - One-Act Plays/Barnes' People, circa 1989-1990 (Box 5)
    - Madame Zenobia
    - Slaughterman
    - The Road to Strome
    - A True-Born Englishman
  - No End to Dreaming (Box 5)
  - Sunsets and Glories, circa 1985 (Box 5)
  - Tango at the End of Winter, circa 1991 (Box 5)
  - Bye Bye Columbus, circa 1991; 3 (Box 5)
  - The Dark Lady, 1992 (Box 5)
  - The Trial of Socrates, 1992 (Box 5)
  - The Enchanted April, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Eggs in Gravy, circa 1992 (Box 5)
  - Hard Times, 1993 (Box 6)
  - The Head Invents, the Heart Discovers, 1995 (Box 6)
  - After All the Rest Have Gone Home, 1995 (Box 6)
  - Heaven's Blessings, circa 1996 (Box 6)
  - What Comes of Dreaming, circa 1996 (Box 6)
    Titled "Dreaming" in production.
  - Porno Poems, circa 1970-1990 (Box 6)
  - Drummer, circa 1980-1990 (Box 6)
  - Polly, circa 1980-1990 (Box 6)
  - Luna Park Eclipses, Part III: Cast Up on the Coast of Japan, circa 1980-2000 (Box 6)
  - Fungus, circa 1980-2000 (Box 6)
  - Pride, circa 1980-2000 (Box 6)
  - The Butterfly Effect, circa 1980-2000 (Box 6)
- Audiovisual Material, 1976-1992; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged by format.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 7 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Audiocassettes of BBC Productions of Peter Barnes's Plays, 4; Actors (Parts 1 and 2) missing (according to previous title note)
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Barnes' People (1 of 2), undated; 1; 01:24:14; The program begins and ends abruptly. Static is on the tape. The program is distorted at times. Audio in the right channel is recorded at a lower level. (Box 7, Item barcode 39002104615712)
      There is a list of contents included with this audiocassette.
      Alec Guinness, "Confessions of a PTMRC"
      John Clements, "Jumping Mimuses"
      Peggy Ashcroft, "Yesterday's News"
      Leo McLeon, "End of World"
      Dilys Laye, "Belly Dancing"
      John Gielgud, "Glory"
      Judi Dench, "Rosa"
      Critics
    - Barnes' People (2 of 2), undated; 1; 00:47:34; High background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. The program ends abruptly. (Box 7, Item barcode 39002104615720)
      Contents on this audiocassette include: "Rosa", critics, "Belly" and "Glory".
    - Barnes' People II, undated; 1; 01:53:34; High background noise is on the tape. Audio is at times weak or hollow. The program is distorted at times. Static can be heard on the tape. Audio in the right channel was recorded at a lower level. (Box 7, Item barcode 39002104615738)
      Worms
      It's Cold, Wanderer, It's Cold
      The Righ Time and Place
      Acting Exercise
      Silver Bridges
      Moondog Rogan and the Mighty Hamster
      Lament for Armenians and Grey Viruses
    - Actors, Parts 3 and 4, undated; 1; 01:09:03; High background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. A high amount of buzz and static can be heard on the tape. (Box 7, Item barcode 39002104615746)
  - DVD-R files and VHS tapes of Peter Barnes's movies and television plays (copies), 1976-1992
    - Leonardo's Last Supper (DVD-R), 1976
    - Leonardo's Last Supper, 1976; GENMSS625_0001; 1; 00:49:03 (Box 7, Item barcode 39002102301554)
    - Revolutionary Witness: The Patriot, The Preacher, The Butcher, The Amazon (DVD-R), 1989
    - Revolutionary Witness: The Patriot, The Preacher, The Butcher, The Amazon, 1989; GENMSS625_0002; 1; 01:19:20 (Box 7, Item barcode 39002102301562)
    - The Spirit of Man (DVD-R), 1989
    - Nobody Here but Us Chickens, More than a Touch of Zen, Not as Bad as They Seem (DVD-R), 1989
    - Enchanted April (DVD-R), 1992
    - Bye Bye Columbus (DVD-R), 1992
- Other Papers, 1958-2007; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged in the order in which material was received by the library.
  - Photographs of world premiere production of "Sunsets and Glories", circa 1990-1992 (Box 8)
    17 photographs, including one duplicate, plus 1 photograph of West Yorkshire Playhouse.
  - Program of world premiere production of "Sunsets and Glories", 1990 (Box 8)
  - Programs of premieres, 1981-2001 (Box 8)
  - Writings by Barnes (photocopies), circa 1958-1997 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence between Gisele Joly and Bernard F. Dukore concerning a French translation of Barnes's "Red Noses.", 2007 (Box 8)
  - Photographs: "Heaven's Blessings", 1997 (Box 8)
    7 photographs of first production of "Heaven's Blessings" at Florida State Univeristy.
  - Interview Transcripts, 1990-1993 (Box 8)
    Transcripts of three interviews with Barnes by Dukore.
  - Published Interviews (photocopies), 1970-1998 (Box 8)
    Interviews with Barnes by Dukore and others.
  - Reviews, promotional articles, obituary, 1978-2004 (Box 8)
  - Writings by Dukore on Barnes (clippings and photocopies), 1981-1995 (Box 8)
  - Alice in Wonderland: Concept Designs and Ideas, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Diary by Dukore, recording rehearsals of the Royal Shakespeare Company's production of Red Noses, 1985 February-July (Box 8)
  - Photocopies of correspondence and report concerning the plagiarism lawsuit of Milton Rokeach against Peter Barnes, 1978 (Box 8)
- Computer media, 0.21; (1 box)
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - LEONARDO'S LAST SUPPER (1976): 47, 2008-genm-19655-0001; 1 (Box 9)
    Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - REVOLUTIONARY WITNESS: THE PATRIOT, THE PREACHER, THE BUTCHER, THE AMAZON (1989) 1:19, 2008-genm-19655-0002; 1 (Box 9)
  - THE SPIRIT OF MAN (1989) 1:06, 2008-genm-19655-0003; 1 (Box 9)
  - NOBODY HERE BUT US CHICKENS, MORE THAN A TOUCH OF ZEN, NOT AS BAD AS THEY SEEM (1989) 1:08, 2008-genm-19655-0004; 1 (Box 9)
  - ENCHANTED APRIL (1992) 1:34, 2008-genm-19655-0005; 1 (Box 9)
  - BYE BYE COLUMBUS (1992) 48 min., 2008-genm-19655-0006; 1 (Box 9)